James Luther Adams Foundation Collection
James Luther Adams Foundation Collection
1976-2018
James Luther Adams Foundation.
2.5 linear ft.
Material from their lecture series, JLA Forum on Religion and Society (brochures, texts of lectures, etc.) as well as audiorecordings and videorecordings of or by Adams.
4124027
Biographical History
James Luther Adams (1901-1994) was a Unitarian parish minister, social activist, journal editor, distinguished scholar, translator and editor of major German theologians, prolific author, and highly respected divinity school professor for more than forty years. Adams played a pivotal role in the shaping of the discipline of social ethics in the United States.
The James Luther Adams Foundation is devoted to the promulgation of Adams' work and ideas. Its two primary projects are the preservation and distribution of The Adams Tapes, a series of films about the church and Nazism, and the maintenance of Adams' intellectual heritage through the James Luther Adams Forum on Religion and Society.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The James Luther Adams Foundation Collection consists primarily of material from the James Luther Adams Forum on Religion and Society, including lectures and other material. Material from each forum is filed separately. There is also material on Other Events, copies of some Recordings made or re-recorded by the Foundation and Miscellaneous material related to James Luther Adams.
Arrangement of the Collection
Chronological.
Related Material
See also the
James Luther Adams Papers
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Activism and social reform; Church and clergy; Religion and Philosophy; Adams, James Luther, 1901-1994.; James Luther Adams Foundation.; Church and state -- Germany.; Church and state -- United States.; Religion and ethics.; Religion and state -- Germany.; Religion and state -- United States.; Theology -- Study and teaching.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Religious aspects.; Clippings (information artifacts); Digital Betacam (TM); Documentary film.; DVDs.; Home movies.; Lectures.; Sound recordings.; VHS.; Video recordings.; Theologians.; Ethicists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Stephen Mott and others, on behalf of the James Luther Adams Foundation.
Accruals
Approximately annual.
Inventory
- James Luther Adams Forum on Religion and Society
  - List of forums, to 2018 (Box 1)
  - 1st forum, Nov 1996; program; lecture by Max L. Stackhouse; contributors list; song book (Box 1)
  - 4th forum, Apr 2000; program; lecture by George Pickering (Box 1)
  - 7th, 2003; jlaf_036, jlaf_037; program; lecture by David Little; two CDs with audiorecordings of speakers (Box 1)
  - 8th forum, 2004; lecture by Robin W. Lovin (Box 1)
  - 10th forum, Apr 2006; lecture by Rosemary Radford Ruether (Box 1)
  - 11th forum, 2007; program; lecture by Harvey Cox (Box 1)
  - 12th forum, 2008; introductory remarks, opening remarks, papers, etc.; includes expansion of one paper as published in Crosscurrents; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 13th forum, Jan 2009; program; lecture by Patrick D. Miller (Box 1)
  - 14th forum, Oct 2009; lecture by Don Brown, including published version in Criterion, Vol. 47, No. 3 (Box 1)
  - 15th forum, Mar 2011; lecture by John R. Wilcox (Box 1)
  - 16th forum, Nov 2011; lecture by George Kimmich Beach (Box 1)
  - 18th forum, Mar 2014; lecture by Michael S. Hogue (Box 1)
  - 19th forum, Aug 2014; lectures by Virgil Stucker and Brian Snyder (Box 1)
  - 20th forum, Nov 2015; jlaf_038; program flyer with sponsor list; lecture by Gary Dorrien; DVD (Box 1)
  - 21st forum, Feb 2016; lecture by Chris Hedges (Box 1)
  - 22nd forum, Nov 2017; lecture by Dan Mckanan (Box 1)
- Other Events
  - Colloquia, Conferences, Oct 1999; Apr 2006; papers by Nathaniel Lauriat and Norm Faramelli (Box 1)
  - Essay Contest, Apr 2013; essay by Florence Caplow (Box 1)
  - JLA Birthday, 80th, 1981; 1982; Publication in the Union Seminary Quarterly Review of papers given at the James Luther Adams Festival with contributions by Donald W. Shriver, Jr, Max L. Stackhouse, David Little, M. Gregor Goethals, Theodore M. Steerman (Box 1)
  - JLA Birthday, 85th, Nov 1986; programs; with contributions by George K. Beach, Michelle Bouvier Campagnolo, Judy Deutsch, Hubert Jessup, Jim Hunt, Doris Hunter, David B. Parke, Marion Pauck, William F. Schulz, Max L. Stackhouse, Garrick Utley, George Huntston Williams, Loretta J. Williams, Conrad Wright (Box 1)
- Recordings
  - The Adams Tapes, 1991-1992; jlaf_001, jlaf_002; Volume I: No Authority But From God; Volume II: Religion Under Hitler; Volume III: Liberalism and the Barmen Declaration in Nazi Germany; 2 DVDs (Box 2)
  - The Adams Tapes, 1991-1992; jlaf_005; Volume I: No Authority But From God; Volume II: Religion Under Hitler; Volume III: Liberalism and the Barmen Declaration in Nazi Germany; 3 VHS tapes (Oversize 1)
  - Christian Leaders of Nazi Germany, jlaf_006; according to donor, these are "8mm home movies that JLA took in 1935-36 Germany"; film-to-tape transfer of 8mm black-and-white reversal; 1 digital Betacam tape (Oversize 1)
  - Christian Leaders of Nazi Germany, copies, jlaf_007, jlaf_008; copies of the above; 2 DVDs (Oversize 1)
  - James Luther Adams, 1936 Christian Leaders, jlaf_009; according to donor, these are "8mm home movies that JLA took in 1935-36 Germany"; film-to-tape transfer of 8mm black-and-white reversal; 1 digital Betacam tape (Oversize 1)
  - James Luther Adams, 1936 Christian Leaders, copies, jlaf_010, jlaf_011; copies of the above; 2 DVDs (Oversize 1)
  - James Luther Adams and George Hunston Williams discuss Christian leaders of Nazi Germany, undated; jlaf_012 through jlaf_029; 18 VHS tapes (Oversize 1)
  - James Luther Adams at home, undated; jlaf_030; home movies? (Oversize 1)
  - Storm Troopers of Christ: Baptism and the Jews in the Third Reich, undated; jlaf_031; commercial DVD, possibly produced by Vital Visuals; no author or company name appears on the case; 1 DVD (Box 2)
  - Strasburg, jlaf_032; according to donor, these are "8mm home movies that JLA took in 1935-36 Germany"; film-to-tape transfer of 8mm black-and-white reversal; 1 digital Betacam tape (Oversize 1)
  - Strasburg, copies, jlaf_033, jlaf_034; copies of the above; 2 DVDs (Oversize 1)
  - Unity, undated; jlaf_035; 1 VHS tape (Box 2)
- Miscellany
  - Clippings, 1994; 1996,; 2000,; 2003; about JLA (Box 2)
  - JLA Foundation, about etc., about JLA Foundation (Box 2)
  - Memorabilia, 1976; 1982; about JLA (Box 2)